はいはーい！
莉莉娅：嗨嗨——！
Hi-hi!
というわけで、皆様おはようございます
莉莉娅：总之，各位早上好。
So, good morning everyone.
毎度おなじみという体裁でいきなりお送りします
莉莉娅：虽然很突然，但还是以老样子的形式为您播出。
We're bringing this to you suddenly, as if it were a regular thing.
『救ってもらっていいですか？ラジオ』のお時間がやって参りました
莉莉娅：《可以来拯救吗？广播》的时间到了。
It's time for the "Will You Save Us? Radio."
ちょっと待て！
史旺：等一下！
Wait a minute!
今回のお相手はあたし
莉莉娅：本次的主持人是我。
Your host this time is me.
五百年前の地上でセニオリス振り回しながら
莉莉娅：五百年前在地上挥舞着瑟尼欧里斯，
The one who swung Seniorious around on the surface 500 years ago,
人類最強勇者とかやってました
莉莉娅：当着什么人类最强勇者的——
serving as the strongest human hero...
リーリァ・アスプレイと
莉莉娅：莉莉娅·阿斯普雷伊，以及——
Lillia Asplay, and...
こいつに引っ張り回されてた貧乏くじパーティーの一名
莉莉娅：被这家伙到处折腾的倒霉蛋队伍中的一员——
One of the members of the unlucky party who got dragged around by her...
後の大賢者となるスウォン・カンデルで
莉莉娅：日后成为大贤者的史旺·坎德尔——
Suowong Kandel, who would later become the Great Sage...
お送りしまーす
莉莉娅：为您播出——
Bringing this to you...
じゃなくて！
史旺：才不是咧！
Wait, no!
何をさっきから……
史旺：从刚才开始就在说什么……
What have you been saying since...
いや「何を」じゃないだろ
史旺：不对，什么“什么”啊，
No, not "what,"
何なんだよこの脚本！
史旺：这剧本是怎么回事！
what is with this script?!
ラジオって何だよ！
史旺：广播又是什么鬼！
What is a "Radio"?!
僕たちの知ってていいものじゃないよな？
史旺：那不是我们该知道的东西吧？
That's not something we're supposed to know about, right?
一応曲がりなりにもファンタジーっぽい世界の住人として
史旺：好歹我们也算是奇幻风格世界的居民，
Even if it's a stretch, as residents of a fantasy-like world,
喋っていい言葉じゃないよな？
史旺：说这种词真的好吗？
should we be using words like that?
うん、何を今更
莉莉娅：嗯，事到如今还说什么呢。
Yeah, why bring that up now?
言っとくけどこの特典ドラマシリーズ
莉莉娅：我先说好，这个特典广播剧系列，
Just so you know, this bonus drama series
ここまで半分くらいが世界観完全無視でやってきてんのよ
莉莉娅：到现在为止有一半左右都是完全无视世界观的哦。
has completely ignored the world setting for about half of it up to this point.
ラジオネタだって二回目だし
莉莉娅：广播梗这已经是第二次了。
This is the second time we've done a radio bit.
いや開き直るとこじゃないだろそれ！
史旺：喂，这不是该破罐子破摔的地方吧！
That's not something you should be shameless about!
あ、いいのいいの
莉莉娅：啊，没事的没事的。
Ah, it's fine, it's fine.
監督さんにもちゃんと確認したし
莉莉娅：我也好好跟导演确认过了。
I confirmed it with the director.
せっかく番外編最終回なんだし
莉莉娅：难得是番外篇最终回，
Since it's the final extra episode,
楽屋落ち連打してもいいですか？って
莉莉娅：我就问“能不能连续爆内幕梗啊？”
I asked, "Is it okay to drop a bunch of meta jokes?"
メタ発言遠慮ないな！
史旺：你的メタ发言真是不客气啊！
You really hold nothing back with the meta comments!
流石に隠せよそういうのは！
史旺：这种事情好歹掩饰一下啊！
You should at least try to hide that sort of thing!
『いいですよ〜』って、すごく引きつった顔のOKもらった
莉莉娅：他说“可以哟~”，然后一脸抽搐地给了我OK。
He said "Sure~" and gave me an OK with a very twitchy face.
色々ダメじゃないか！
史旺：各种意义上都不行吧！
That sounds bad on so many levels!
遠慮とかしとけよそこは！
史旺：那种地方你要懂得客气啊！
You should have held back there!
本編の物悲しい余韻とか
莉莉娅：我想把正篇那种悲伤的余韵，
The sorrowful lingering mood of the main story...
そういうの全力でぶち壊したい
莉莉娅：之类的东西全力破坏掉。
I want to completely destroy that sort of thing.
なぜなら、あたしの出番あまりなかったから！
莉莉娅：因为，我根本没什么出场机会啊！
Because I barely had any screen time!
ね！
莉莉娅：对吧！
Right?!
同意求めるなよ
史旺：别寻求我的同意啊。
Don't ask for my agreement.
どんな返事を期待してるんだよ
史旺：你期待我给什么回答啊。
What kind of answer are you expecting?
人生ノリと思いきりが大事
莉莉娅：人生最重要的就是气势和果断。
In life, vibe and decisiveness are important.
半端な固定観念に縛られてるようじゃ
莉莉娅：如果被半吊子的固有观念束缚，
If you're bound by half-hearted stereotypes,
激動の週末時代は生き抜けないぜ？
莉莉娅：可是没法在动荡的周末时代幸存的哦？
you won't survive this turbulent weekend era, you know?
いやいやどういう時代だよ
史旺：不不，那是什么时代啊。
Wait, what kind of era is that?
おかしいだろ
史旺：很奇怪吧。
That's weird.
徹頭徹尾何もかもが
史旺：彻头彻尾都很奇怪啊。
Everything about this, from start to finish.
もう、聞き分け悪いなぁ
莉莉娅：真是的，你也太不听话了。
Geez, you're so stubborn.
しょうがない
莉莉娅：没办法。
Can't be helped.
ちょっと、こっち来て
莉莉娅：稍微，过来一下。
Hey, come here a sec.
おい何だよ、引っ張るなよ
史旺：喂干嘛啊，别拉我啊。
Hey, what? Don't pull me.
音声さんすみません、ちょっとだけマイクオフでお願いします
莉莉娅：音响师不好意思，麻烦稍微把麦克风关一下。
Sorry, sound guy. Could you cut the mic for just a moment?
がっ！うっ……
史旺：嘎！唔……
Gah! Ugh...
暴力……はんたーい……
史旺：反对……暴力……
I oppose... violence...
さて、スウォンが静かになったところで、タイトルコール入りまーす
莉莉娅：好了，趁史旺安静下来了，我们来念标题吧！
Now that Suowong has quieted down, let's do the title call!
終末なにしてますか？忙しいですか？救ってもらっていいですか？
莉莉娅：末日时在做什么？有没有空？可以来拯救吗？
What do you do at the end of the world? Are you busy? Will you save us?
スペシャルオーディオドラマ
莉莉娅：特别广播剧。
Special Audio Drama.
『救ってもらっていいですか？』
莉莉娅：《可以来拯救吗？》
"Will You Save Us?"
では、早速今日のゲストをお呼びしてみましょう
莉莉娅：那么，让我们立刻请出今天的嘉宾。
Now, let's invite today's guest right away.
この男がいなければ、話が始まらないし終わらない
莉莉娅：要是没有这个男人，故事既不会开始也不会结束。
Without this man, the story wouldn't start or end.
時を超えても女泣かせ
莉莉娅：即使跨越时空也总是惹女人哭泣。
Making women cry even across time.
世界で一番罪な男（あたし調べ、カッコ閉じ）
莉莉娅：世界上最罪孽深重的男人（据我调查，括号闭）。
The most sinful man in the world (according to my research, close parenthesis).
五百年後バージョンの、ヴィレムさーん！
莉莉娅：五百年后版本的，威廉先生——！
The 500-years-later version, Mr. Willem!
ふごっ、ぐふっ……
威廉：呼唔，咕呼……
Mmph, guh...
あーしまったしまった
莉莉娅：啊糟了糟了，
Ah, oops, my bad.
無理やり拉致してきた時に猿轡かませてたの忘れてた
莉莉娅：忘了强行绑架来的时候还塞着口球呢。
I forgot I gagged him when I forcibly abducted him.
ふごぉぉ……
威廉：唔唔唔……
Mmmph...
はいはい、今取ってあげるからね、大人しくしててね
莉莉娅：好啦好啦，现在就帮你取下来，要乖乖的哦。
Okay, okay, I'll take it off now. Be a good boy.
えい
莉莉娅：嘿。
There.
ぷはっ！
威廉：普哈！
Pwah!
はぁ……はぁ……はぁ……
威廉：哈……哈……哈……
Haa... haa... haa...
はい、というわけで、ゲストのヴィレム・クメシュさん
莉莉娅：好，综上所述，嘉宾威廉·克梅修先生。
Okay, so, our guest is Mr. Willem Kmetsch.
最強勇者のお仲間の一人で
莉莉娅：最强勇者的伙伴之一，
One of the companions of the strongest hero,
才能がなくて最強にちょっぴり足りなかった残念な人
莉莉娅：因为没有才能而离最强只差一点点的遗憾之人。
a regrettable person who lacked the talent to be the strongest by just a bit.
その辺細かい紹介は面倒くさいから省略しまして
莉莉娅：那些细节介绍太麻烦了就省略掉。
Detailed introductions are a hassle, so we'll skip that.
では、今のお気持ちを一言
莉莉娅：那么，请说一句现在的感想。
Now, a word on how you're feeling.
死ぬかと思った
威廉：我还以为要死了。
I thought I was going to die.
うんうん、大変な世界になってたもんね、五百年後の空の上
莉莉娅：嗯嗯，毕竟变成了很不得了的世界呢，五百年后的天空之上。
Yeah, yeah. It became quite a difficult world, up in the sky 500 years later.
いやそっちの方の話じゃなくてだな
威廉：不，我说的不是那方面的事。
No, I'm not talking about that.
最初は言葉も通じなかったんでしょ？よく無事に生きていけたわよね
莉莉娅：刚开始语言也不通吧？真亏你能平安活下来呢。
At first, you couldn't even understand the language, right? It's amazing you survived.
生水飲んだりしなかった？サイズの合うパンツとか売ってた？
莉莉娅：没喝生水吧？有卖尺寸合适的内裤吗？
Did you drink raw water? Did they sell underwear in your size?
なんだそりゃ
威廉：那都什么鬼。
What is that?
いやまぁ言葉については通話術師を雇ったり
威廉：嘛，关于语言，雇佣了通化术师
Well, regarding the language, I could hire translators
言語理解のタリスマンを使ったりできたから
威廉：或者使用语言理解护符之类的。
or use language comprehension talismans...
そこまで苦労はなかったな
威廉：所以并没有那么辛苦。
...so it wasn't that much of a struggle.
ありゃ、なんか真面目な答え
莉莉娅：哎呀，回答得好正经。
Oh my, what a serious answer.
身振り手振り尻尾振りでなんとかした、みたいな答え期待してたのに
莉莉娅：我还期待你会回答“靠着比划手势摇尾巴总算搞定了”之类的呢。
I was expecting an answer like "I managed with gestures and tail wagging."
ねぇよ、特に尻尾はねぇよ
威廉：才没有，特别是尾巴绝对没有。
No way. Especially no tail.
じゃあ生水は？パンツのサイズは？
莉莉娅：那生水呢？内裤尺寸呢？
Then what about raw water? Underwear size?
飲むわけねぇし、そこで困りもしねぇよ
威廉：才不会喝，那方面也没遇到困难。
I wouldn't drink it, and I didn't have trouble with the other thing either.
そりゃ大小極端な連中も多かったけどな
威廉：虽说体型极端大小的家伙也很多。
Sure, there were a lot of guys with extreme sizes.
俺くらいの体格の奴らだってそれなりに住んでんだからな
威廉：但我这种体格的家伙也住着不少。
But there are plenty of people with my build living there too.
まぁケツの所に穴が空いてんのは参ったけどよ
威廉：虽然屁股那里开了个洞让我挺头疼就是了。
Though I was annoyed that there were holes in the butt area.
やはり尻尾か、生やしたか
莉莉娅：果然是尾巴吗，你长尾巴了吗？
So it is the tail. Did you grow one?
生やさねぇよ
威廉：没长啦。
I didn't grow one.
ん、でもよかった
莉莉娅：嗯，不过太好了。
Hmm, but that's good.
結構楽しそうにやってたみたいじゃない
莉莉娅：看来你过得还挺开心的嘛。
It sounds like you were having a pretty good time.
いい出会いとかたくさんあったみたいだし
莉莉娅：似乎也有很多不错的相遇。
Looks like you had lots of good encounters.
ちょっと心配してたんだぞ
莉莉娅：我可是稍微有点担心你哦？
I was actually a little worried about you, you know?
お、おう
威廉：哦、哦。
O-Oh.
あんたほら、人間関係不器用なとこあるし
莉莉娅：你看你这人，在人际关系上有点笨拙。
You know, you can be clumsy with relationships.
人からの好意から逃げようとするし
莉莉娅：又总是想逃避别人的好意。
And you try to run away from people's affection.
そのくせして貧乏くじはズルしてでも自分で引こうとするしさ
莉莉娅：明明这样，却还要作弊去抽下下签把倒霉事揽给自己。
Yet you'll cheat just to draw the short straw yourself.
そりゃまぁ、そうなんだけどよ
威廉：那个嘛，确实是那样啦。
Well... I guess that's true.
お、どうしたの？そっぽ向いちゃって
莉莉娅：哦？怎么了？把脸别过去。
Oh? What's wrong? Looking away like that.
お前が労るみたいな声出すと、なんか企んでるみたいで落ち着かねぇ
威廉：你用这种关心的语气说话，总觉得像是在谋划什么，让我静不下心。
When you use that caring voice, it feels like you're plotting something, and it makes me nervous.
へぇ、何かあるたびにヒョイヒョイ手が出てくるくらいの方が
莉莉娅：嘿，你是说那种动不动就随意出手的样子，
Heh, so you're saying being quick to throw a punch whenever something happens
いつものお前らしいって？
莉莉娅：更像平时的你吗？
is more like you?
ああ……そういうこと言うか
威廉：啊……你是那个意思吗，
Ah... is that what you're saying?
言っちゃうのかこの口は
威廉：这张嘴还真敢说啊……
Is that mouth really saying that?
じゃ、遠慮なく
莉莉娅：那我就不客气了。
Then, don't mind if I do.
ねぇ！？
威廉：喂！？
Hey?!
いっっっ……！
威廉：痛……！
Oww...!
しょうのない兄弟子の教育は、妹弟子の義務だからな
莉莉娅：教育那个无可救药的师兄是师妹的义务嘛，
Educating the hopeless senior disciple is the junior disciple's duty, after all.
しょうがないな
莉莉娅：没办法啊。
Can't be helped.
あああ、いやこれガチで痛ぇぞ！関節どういう決め方してんだ！
威廉：啊啊啊，不这真的超痛啊！你这关节技是怎么锁的啊！
Aaaah, no, this seriously hurts! How are you locking my joints?!
正規勇者八十八の関節技の一つだし
莉莉娅：这可是正规勇者八十八关节技之一。
It's one of the 88 joint techniques of the True Heroes.
肉と骨があれば神様にだって決まるってお墨付きだし
莉莉娅：是有着“只要有肉和骨头，连神也能锁住”的权威认证的。
It's guaranteed to work even on gods as long as they have flesh and bone.
実際前に試した時には一本へし折れたし
莉莉娅：实际上之前试的时候还折断过一根呢。
Actually, I snapped one when I tried it before.
適当言って……ああっ！
威廉：胡说什么……啊啊！
You're just making that up... Aaah!
なんてことでしょう
莉莉娅：这可怎么办呢。
Oh my goodness.
また新たな犠牲者が出てしまった
莉莉娅：又出现了新的牺牲者。
Another victim has appeared.
いくらあたしでも、一人きりでは番組の進行に差し障りが出てしまう
莉莉娅：就算是我，只有一个人也会影响节目进行的。
Even I can't run the program all by myself without issues.
誰のせいだよ！
威廉：是谁的错啊！
Whose fault is that?!
てい！
莉莉娅：嘿！
Tei!
あがっ！
威廉：啊嘎！
Agah!
はいはい、スウォンは静かにしててね
莉莉娅：好啦好啦，史旺你就安静点哦。
Okay, okay, be quiet now, Suowong.
というわけで、二人目のゲストを呼んでみたいと思います
莉莉娅：那么，我想请出第二位嘉宾。
So, I'd like to invite our second guest.
なんだと？聞いてねぇぞ
威廉：什么？我没听说啊。
What? I didn't hear about this.
うん、言ってなかったから
莉莉娅：嗯，因为我没说嘛。
Yeah, because I didn't tell you.
どうせまたろくでもない奴なんだろうな
威廉：反正又是不像话的家伙吧。
It's probably another good-for-nothing.
では、特別ゲストの、アルちゃん！
莉莉娅：有请特别嘉宾，爱尔酱！
Now, our special guest, Al-chan!
は〜い！
爱尔梅莉亚：嗨——！
Hiii!
アルマリアさん！？
威廉：爱尔梅莉亚小姐！？
Ms. Almaria?!
うわ、復活した
史旺：哇，复活了。
Whoa, he revived.
というわけで、何だか楽しそうだったのでお呼ばれしました
爱尔梅莉亚：总之，看这里好像很有趣，所以我就应邀而来了。
Anyway, it looked fun, so I was invited.
お父さんの娘の、アルマリア・デュフナーです
爱尔梅莉亚：我是爸爸的女儿，爱尔梅莉亚·杜夫纳。
I'm Dad's daughter, Almaria Dufna.
今日はよろしくお願いします
爱尔梅莉亚：今天请多关照。
Nice to meet you all today.
ってコラ、アル！
威廉：喂，爱尔！
Hey, Al!
怪しい人に声かけられてもホイホイついて行くなと教えたろうが！
威廉：我不是教过你就算被可疑的人搭话也不要随随便便跟过去吗！
Didn't I teach you not to just follow suspicious people who talk to you?!
そいつの怪しさは人類最高峰から数えて
威廉：那家伙的可疑程度
Her suspiciousness ranks
堂々二番目だぞ！
威廉：在人类最高峰里可是堂堂排名第二啊！
a proud second among the peak of humanity!
そうですよ、自分を大事にしてください
莉莉娅：就是说啊，请爱惜自己。
That's right, please value yourself.
あんたら……コラ二人！
威廉：你们……喂，你们俩！
You guys... Hey, you two!
二人とも仲良しなのは知ってるけど
爱尔梅莉亚：我知道你们两个关系很好，
I know you two are close,
それとこれとは別問題
爱尔梅莉亚：但一码归一码。
but that's a separate issue.
女の子を怪しい人呼ばわりなんて感心しないんだから
爱尔梅莉亚：把女孩子叫作可疑的人我可不佩服哦。
Calling a girl "suspicious person" isn't very nice.
女の子……？女の子ぉ！？
威廉：女……孩子……？女孩子！？
Girl...? A girl?!
いや、いわゆる女の子ってのは
威廉：不，所谓的“女孩子”，
No, so-called "girls"
殺人級の関節技を使ったりはしねぇ……
威廉：是不会使用杀人级关节技的……
don't use lethal joint locks...
あら、あれは何だ？
爱尔梅莉亚：哎呀，那是什么？
Oh my, what's that?
え？
威廉：欸？
Huh?
てい！
爱尔梅莉亚：嘿！
Tei!
ひぃぃぃ……ぎゃあああ！
威廉：咿咿咿……啊啊啊！
Hieeee... Gyaaaah!
んー、何もないですよー
爱尔梅莉亚：唔，什么都没有哦——
Hmm, nothing there.
ありゃ？
爱尔梅莉亚：哎呀？
Oh?
あー、やっぱりアルちゃんはいい子だわ
莉莉娅：啊——爱尔酱果然是个好孩子啊。
Ah, Al-chan really is a good girl.
うちにも一人欲しいわ
莉莉娅：我也想要一个这样的孩子。
I want one for my family too.
あ、あの、なんかお父さんとスウォン君
爱尔梅莉亚：啊，那个，爸爸和史旺君
Ah, um, it looks like Dad and Suowong-kun
泡吹いて倒れてるんですけど
爱尔梅莉亚：好像口吐白沫倒在地上了。
are foaming at the mouth and collapsed.
うんうん、さっき腹減ったとか言って石鹸食べてたからね
莉莉娅：嗯嗯，刚才他们喊肚子饿吃了肥皂呢，
Yeah, yeah. They were saying they were hungry and ate soap earlier.
多分そのせいだね
莉莉娅：大概是因为那个吧。
Probably because of that.
とりあえず邪魔だから、二人とも部屋の外に出しとこっか
莉莉娅：总之很碍事，把他们两个都扔到房间外面去吧。
They're in the way, so let's just put them both outside the room.
それでよし
莉莉娅：这样就好。
There we go.
んじゃ、失礼な兄弟子のことは放っといて、お話ししよ？お話し
莉莉娅：那么，别管那个失礼的师兄了，来聊天吧？聊天。
So, let's ignore that rude senior disciple and talk, shall we? Talk.
あ、はい
爱尔梅莉亚：啊，好的。
Ah, okay.
というわけで、改めましてアルちゃん
莉莉娅：总之，再次欢迎爱尔酱。
So, once again, welcome Al-chan.
本編で全くと言っていいくらい出番がなかった同士
莉莉娅：作为在正篇中几乎可以说完全没有出场的同伴，
As comrades who had practically zero screen time in the main story,
よろしくお願いします
莉莉娅：请多关照。
nice to meet you.
あ、はい！よろしくお願いします
爱尔梅莉亚：啊，好的！请多关照。
Ah, yes! Nice to meet you too.
んでもって早速本題、っていうか
莉莉娅：那么直接进入正题，或者说
Now, straight to the main topic.
今日はこの話を聞きたくてアルちゃんを呼んだと言っても過言ではない
莉莉娅：我今天是为了问这件事才叫爱尔酱来的也不为过。
It's no exaggeration to say I invited Al-chan today just to hear about this.
まずほら、あたしらって物理的に過去の女なわけよね
莉莉娅：首先你看，我们在物理层面上已经是过去的女人了对吧。
First off, you know, we're physically "women of the past."
んで、あたしらがくたばった五百年後に
莉莉娅：然后，在我们挂了五百年后，
And 500 years after we kicked the bucket,
あのヴィレムはちゃっかり若い子といい感じになってたりするわけです
莉莉娅：那个威廉竟然和年轻的女孩子搞得火热。
that Willem is shrewdly getting cozy with a young girl.
みたいですね
爱尔梅莉亚：好像是呢。
Seems like it.
その辺につきまして、義理というか
莉莉娅：关于这一点，我想请作为义理……
Regarding that, I'd like to get a comment from you, his daughter-in-law...
成り行きの親子であるアルちゃんに、コメントを頂きたいですね
莉莉娅：或者说顺势成为父女的爱尔酱发表一下评论。
or rather, daughter by circumstance.
どんな感じ？やっぱ若い子がいいのねとか
莉莉娅：感觉如何？果然还是年轻的好啊之类的，
How does it feel? Like "I guess he prefers younger girls"
私たちというものがありながら……とか
莉莉娅：或者是明明还有我们……之类的？
or "Even though he had us..."?
うーん、そういうのとはちょっと違うんですけど
爱尔梅莉亚：唔，跟那种感觉不太一样呢。
Hmm, it's not quite like that.
ほら、うちのお父さんってあんな感じの人だから
爱尔梅莉亚：你看，我家爸爸是那种性格的人。
You know, my dad is that kind of person.
ちゃんと彼女とか作れるのかなって結構不安だったんですよね
爱尔梅莉亚：能不能好好交到女朋友什么的，我其实挺不安的。
I was actually pretty worried about whether he could properly get a girlfriend.
甘え下手っていうか、余裕ないのに人のことばっかり考えてるとか
爱尔梅莉亚：他不擅长撒娇，明明自己都不宽裕却光想着别人的事。
He's bad at relying on others, and always thinking about others even when he has no room to spare.
根っからの父親気質っていうか
爱尔梅莉亚：可以说是骨子里的父亲气质吧。
He has a fatherly temperament to the core.
あはは、やっぱ身内の目から見てもそんななんだ
莉莉娅：啊哈哈，果然在家里人眼里也是那样啊。
Ahaha, so he looks like that even to his family.
そんななんです。だからお父さんなんです
爱尔梅莉亚：就是那样的。所以才是爸爸，
That's exactly it. That's why he's "Dad,"
お兄ちゃんとかじゃなくて、そんな歳じゃないのにね
爱尔梅莉亚：而不是哥哥之类的，明明还没到那个年纪呢。
not "Big Brother," even though he's not that old.
だから、そんなお父さんが将来ちゃんと女の子を好きになってくれるっていうのがね
爱尔梅莉亚：所以，这样的爸爸将来能好好地喜欢上一个女孩子，
So, the fact that Dad would properly fall in love with a girl in the future...
ちょっと驚きだし、ちょっと嬉しいかなって
爱尔梅莉亚：让我有点惊讶，也有点高兴。
it's a bit surprising, and I guess I'm a bit happy about it.
やっぱほら、娘として父親の幸せはそこはかとなく祈ってたし
爱尔梅莉亚：毕竟作为女儿，还是会隐隐约约祈祷父亲的幸福嘛。
You know, as a daughter, I was vaguely praying for my father's happiness.
えーっと、父親だ娘だって言ったって、血も繋がってないし
莉莉娅：那个，虽说是父亲和女儿，但也没血缘关系，
Um, even if you say father and daughter, you're not related by blood,
歳はほとんど離れてないわけでしょ？
莉莉娅：年龄也没差多少吧？
and your ages aren't that far apart, right?
実は自分が恋人になる気だったとか……
莉莉娅：其实自己想成为恋人什么的……
Actually, you intended to be his lover...
そういう気持ちもあったりは……？
莉莉娅：有没有过这种想法……？
Did you have feelings like that...?
全然！
爱尔梅莉亚：完全没有！
Not at all!
わお、断言した
莉莉娅：哇哦，断言了。
Wow, she declared it.
だってうちのお父さん、恋人より家族をとるタイプですし
爱尔梅莉亚：因为我家爸爸是那种比起恋人更重视家人的类型，
Because my dad is the type to choose family over a lover,
それも筋金入りの
爱尔梅莉亚：而且是铁杆的那种。
and a hardcore one at that.
私今家族なのに、恋人になんかなっちゃったら扱い大幅ランクダウンですよ
爱尔梅莉亚：我现在明明是家人，要是成了恋人待遇可是会大幅下降的，
I'm family right now, so if I became a lover, my treatment would be significantly downgraded.
ただの大損ですよ
爱尔梅莉亚：简直是亏大了。
It would be a huge loss.
あぁ……あぁ……
莉莉娅：啊……啊……
Ah... Ah...
だから、そんなお父さんがちゃんと一人の女の子を選んだっていうのは
爱尔梅莉亚：所以，这样的爸爸竟然好好地选择了一个女孩子，
So, the fact that such a dad properly chose one girl
もう私の中で世界がひっくり返るくらいのビッグニュースなんですよ！
爱尔梅莉亚：这在我心中简直是世界颠覆级别的大新闻啊！
is big enough news to turn my world upside down!
まぁ、事実世界ひっくり返ったしね
莉莉娅：嘛，事实上世界确实颠覆了呢。
Well, the world did literally turn upside down.
でもそっか、アルちゃん的にはそんな感じなのか
莉莉娅：不过是这样啊，对爱尔酱来说是这种感觉啊。
But I see, so that's how it feels for you, Al-chan.
いろいろ納得
莉莉娅：各种理解了。
Makes sense.
そんな感じでした、リーリァさんの方はどうです？
爱尔梅莉亚：就是这种感觉。莉莉娅小姐怎么看呢？
That's how it was. How about you, Miss Lillia?
あたし？あたしは別に何も
莉莉娅：我？我没什么特别的。
Me? I don't really have anything.
本当にそうですか？私、気になります
爱尔梅莉亚：真的是这样吗？我很在意。
Is that really true? I'm curious.
いやいやいや、そんなまた怒られそうな感じに聞かれても
莉莉娅：不不不，你用这种又要被骂的感觉问我……
No, no, no. Even if you ask in a way that sounds like I'm gonna get scolded again...
そもそもあいつはただの兄弟子だし
莉莉娅：那家伙本来就只是个师兄。
He's just a senior disciple anyway.
いや、相当に出来の悪い兄弟子だし
莉莉娅：不，是个相当没用的师兄。
No, he's a pretty incompetent senior disciple.
出来が悪いくせに兄貴風吹かせまくってる鬱陶しい兄弟子だし
莉莉娅：明明没用还总是摆出一副师兄架子的烦人师兄。
An annoying senior disciple who acts bossy despite being incompetent.
誰とくっつこうとそんなに興味はないし
莉莉娅：不管他和谁在一起我都没什么兴趣。
I don't really care who he ends up with.
あー……でも
莉莉娅：啊……不过……
Ah... but...
アルちゃん達がいなくなった後も
莉莉娅：在爱尔酱你们不在之后，
Even after you guys were gone, Al-chan,
あいつがあいつらしく生きてたなら、確かにちょっとは気分いいかな
莉莉娅：如果那家伙还能像他自己一样活着，确实心情稍微好一点吧。
if he lived on being himself, I guess that does make me feel a little better.
ちゃんと家みたいな場所を作って、新しい家族みたいな子達がいて
莉莉娅：好好地建立了一个像家一样的地方，有着像新家人一样的孩子们。
Creating a place like a home, with kids like a new family...
行ってきますって出かけてって、ただいまって帰ってきて
莉莉娅：说着“我出门了”出去，说着“我回来了”回来。
Going out saying "I'm leaving" and coming back saying "I'm home."
やっぱあいつはいつどんな時代にでも、一人になっちゃいけない奴だし
莉莉娅：果然那家伙无论在什么时代，都不能变成孤身一人啊。
After all, no matter the era, he's the kind of guy who shouldn't be alone.
ん？何今の意味深な笑い方
莉莉娅：嗯？刚才那个意味深长的笑法是什么意思？
Hmm? What was that meaningful laugh just now?
何でもないで〜す
爱尔梅莉亚：什么都没有哦——
Nothing at a~ll.
くそっ、関節あちこち思いっきり外しやがって……
威廉：可恶，把各处的关节都狠狠卸下来了……
Damn it, she dislocated joints all over the place...
とか言いながら、自力で復活できるんだな、あの状況から
史旺：嘴上这么说，你还能从那种状况下靠自己复活啊。
You say that, but you can revive yourself from that situation.
そりゃな、瀕死になった程度でいちいち死にかけてたら
威廉：那当然，要是濒死这种程度就要死要活的话，
Of course. If I nearly died every time I was critically injured,
リーリァの兄弟子なんてやってらんねぇぞ
威廉：哪干得了莉莉娅的师兄啊。
I couldn't be Lillia's senior disciple.
うん、何言ってるのか普通に分からない
史旺：嗯，完全听不懂你在说什么。
Yeah, I genuinely don't understand what you're saying.
空が青いとか、市場で可愛いひよこを見たとか
威廉：因为天空很蓝啊，在市场上看到了可爱的小鸡啊，
She'd come at me with a flying kick for reasons like the sky is blue
そんな理由で飛び蹴りかましてくるからな
威廉：她会因为这种理由就飞踢过来。
or she saw a cute chick at the market.
それも一撃で城壁粉砕できる威力のアレ
威廉：而且那是能一击粉碎城墙的威力。
And that kick has the power to shatter castle walls in one hit.
いろいろおかしいだろ、あいつもお前も
史旺：各种意义上都很奇怪吧，不管是她还是你。
You're both weird in so many ways.
いや俺は普通だ。あいつと一緒のカテゴリーには入れるな
威廉：不，我很普通。别把我跟她归为一类，
No, I'm normal. Don't put me in the same category as her;
人としての尊厳に関わる
威廉：这关系到作为人的尊严。
it affects my dignity as a human being.
普通の奴が城壁粉砕キックなんて食らったら死ぬんだよな
史旺：普通人要是吃了城墙粉碎踢可是会死的啊。
A normal person would die if they took a wall-shattering kick.
で、あいつらちゃんと話できてんのか？
威廉：话说，那家伙她们有好好在聊吗？
So, are they managing to talk properly?
え、うわ、それ本当？はぁ……過保護だなぁ
爱尔梅莉亚：诶？哇，那是真的吗？哈……真是过度保护啊。
Eh? Whoa, is that true? Sigh... so overprotective.
本当ですよ、私が他の男の子と話してると
爱尔梅莉亚：真的哦。只要我和其他男孩子说话，
It's true. Whenever I talk to other boys,
すっごく不機嫌になるんです、うちのお父さん
爱尔梅莉亚：我爸爸就会变得超级不高兴。
my dad gets super grumpy.
アルマリアもモテそうだからな。お父さんとしては
威廉：毕竟爱尔梅莉亚看起来很受欢迎嘛。作为父亲，
Almaria seems popular, after all. As a father,
変な男に引っかかりそうで怖いわけだ
威廉：肯定会害怕你被奇怪的男人骗了。
he's scared you'll get caught by some weird guy.
うーん、心配されてること自体は嬉しいんですけどね
爱尔梅莉亚：唔，被担心这件事本身倒是挺开心的啦。
Hmm, I am happy that he worries about me, though.
ふぅん、扉越しじゃ何の話してるのかまでは聞こえねぇが
威廉：哼，隔着门听不清在说什么，
Hmm, I can't hear what they're talking about through the door,
まぁ楽しそうにしてるからよしとするか
威廉：不过看起来聊得很开心就算了吧。
but they seem to be having fun, so I guess it's fine.
ん？アルマリアさん
史旺：嗯？爱尔梅莉亚小姐。
Hmm? Ms. Almaria.
やっぱ可憐だなぁ
史旺：果然很楚楚动人啊……
She really is lovely...
痛った！何すんだよ行きなり！
史旺：好痛！突然干什么啊！
Ouch! What was that for all of a sudden?!
おっと悪い、手が滑った。気をつけろよな全く
威廉：哎呀抱歉，手滑了。给我注意点啊真是的，
Oops, sorry. My hand slipped. Watch yourself, honestly.
お前の拳も十分に危険なんだぞ
威廉：你的拳头也够危险的。
Your fists are dangerous enough too.
はぁ……ところでさ、アルマリアさんって好きな男とかいるのかな？
史旺：哈……话说回来，爱尔梅莉亚小姐有喜欢的男人吗？
Sigh... By the way, does Ms. Almaria have a guy she likes?
おっと悪い、足も滑った
威廉：哎呀抱歉，脚也滑了。
Oops, sorry. My foot slipped too.
おま……ちょっと待て！
史旺：你……等一下！
You... wait a minute!
この障壁は軽く城壁クラスの硬さが……！
史旺：这个屏障可是有城墙级的硬度……！
This barrier is easily castle-wall class in hardness...!
きゅっ
爱尔梅莉亚：Q！
Kyu!
凄い音しましたけど、何ですか今の？
爱尔梅莉亚：刚才好大的声音，发生什么了？
That was a huge noise, what was that?
まぁさてね、どこかの父親の愛が
莉莉娅：谁知道呢，大概是某个父亲的爱，
Well, who knows? Maybe some father's love
今日も誰かに炸裂したんじゃないのかな？
莉莉娅：今天也在某人身上炸裂了吧？
exploded on someone again today?
さて、そろそろお時間がやって参りました
莉莉娅：好了，差不多到了结束的时间了。
Well then, it's about time.
いや〜喋った喋った
莉莉娅：哎呀——聊了好多。
Man, we talked a lot.
本編に出番のなかった腹いせってわけじゃないけど
莉莉娅：虽然不是为了发泄正篇没出场的怨气啦。
Not that I'm venting about not appearing in the main story.
やれやれ、やっと戻ってこれたと思ったら
威廉：哎呀哎呀，好不容易才回来。
Good grief. Just when I thought I finally made it back.
うぅ……頭にコブができた
史旺：呜呜……头上有包了。
Ugh... I got a bump on my head.
お前も大概頑丈だよな
威廉：你也挺结实的嘛。
You're pretty sturdy yourself.
寂しいですが、今回はそろそろお別れということになります
爱尔梅莉亚：虽然很寂寞，但这次差不多要道别了。
It's sad, but it's about time to say goodbye for this time.
次は『終末なにしてますか？（以下略）』二期の
莉莉娅：下次就在《末日时在做什么？（下略）》第二季的
Next time, let's meet in the drama CD bonus for purchasing the disks
ディスク購入特典のドラマCDで会いましょう！って……
莉莉娅：光盘购入特典广播剧中再见吧！这么说……
of the second season of "What Do You Do at the End of the World? (abbreviated)"! Or...
ちょっと待て！
威廉：等一下！
Wait a minute!
何よ大声出して
莉莉娅：干嘛那么大声啊。
Why are you shouting?
大声も出すっての！
威廉：当然要大声了！
Of course I'm shouting!
ドサクサ紛れにとんでもないこと言うな！
威廉：别趁乱说什么不得了的话！
Don't say outrageous things in the confusion!
いろいろデリケートなんだぞその辺の話題は！
威廉：这方面的话题可是很敏感的！
That topic is very delicate!
下手なこと言うと、各方面から怒られるんだぞ！
史旺：乱说话的话，会被各方面骂的哦！
If you say the wrong thing, you'll get yelled at from all sides!
え〜？夢はでっかくもっとかないとでしょ！
莉莉娅：欸——？梦想就是要远大嘛！
Eh? You gotta dream big!
関係者の[ピー]さんとか[ピー]さんとか[ピー]さんとか
莉莉娅：关系者[哔]先生还有[哔]先生还有[哔]先生，
The staff members like [BEEP], [BEEP], and [BEEP]
是非やりたいですねって言ってくださってたし！
莉莉娅：都说很想做呢！
said they'd love to do it!
あーもう！あ、すみません、あ、あの
威廉：啊真是的！啊，不好意思，那个，
Ah, jeez! Oh, sorry. Um,
今の名前の所、編集で、あの消しといてもらえますか
威廉：刚才名字的地方，能不能帮忙剪辑消音一下。
could you edit out the names she just mentioned?
あ大丈夫？あ大丈夫
威廉：啊没问题吗？啊没问题。
Oh, it's okay? Okay.
分かりました、よろしくお願いします
威廉：明白了，拜托了。
Understood, thank you.
だから！夢を……ていうか妄想を！
威廉：所以我说！不要把梦想……或者说妄想！
That's why I'm saying! Don't talk about dreams... or rather, delusions!
あたかも確定事項みたいに語るなって言ってるんだ！
威廉：说得像确定事项一样啊！
As if they're confirmed facts!
色んな人に迷惑がかかるから！
威廉：会给很多人添麻烦的！
It causes trouble for a lot of people!
あ〜、スウォンがいると、代わりに騒いでくれるから
莉莉娅：啊……有史旺在，会替我吵闹，
Ah... having Suowong around makes it easy since he does all the fussing for me.
楽できるなぁ
莉莉娅：真轻松啊。
(Or Willem, she says Suowong but context implies Willem's fuss).
それでは皆様、またお会いしましょう！
莉莉娅：那么各位，下次再见吧！
Well then everyone, let's meet again!
See you next time!
史旺：See you next time!
We will be back!
爱尔梅莉亚：We will be back!
だからそういうの辞めろって言ってんだ！
威廉：都说别那样了！
I told you to stop that!
よし、終わり！はいはい、みんな撤収！お家に帰りましょう！
莉莉娅：好，结束！好了好了，大家撤收！回家啦！
Okay, finished! Alright, alright, everyone pack up! Let's go home!
おかえり
珂朵莉：欢迎回来。
Welcome back.
お？どうしたんすか？技官
格里克：哦？怎么了？技官，
Oh? What's wrong? Tech Officer,
ぐったりして。通りすがりのキメラにでも噛み付かれた？
格里克：无精打采的。是被路过的奇美拉咬了吗？
you look exhausted. Did you get bitten by a passing chimera or something?
そっちの方がまだマシだった
威廉：那样还比较好呢。
That would have been better.
ふん、どうせまた、いらないお節介して
艾瑟雅：哼，反正又是多管闲事
Hmph, you probably meddled where you shouldn't have
トラブルとか抱えてきたんでしょ
艾瑟雅：惹上麻烦了吧。
and got into trouble again.
君って結局、いつだってそんな感じなんだから
艾瑟雅：毕竟你这人，一直都是那个样子。
You're always like that in the end.
あ〜、人を底抜けのお人好しみてぇに言うなって全く……え？
威廉：啊……别把人说得像个烂好人一样真是的……欸？
Ah... don't talk about me like I'm some hopeless do-gooder... Huh?
何？ジロジロ見て
珂朵莉：干嘛？盯着我看。
What? Staring like that.
クトリ……だよな？
威廉：珂朵莉……对吧？
Chtholly... right?
他の誰に見えるの？
珂朵莉：还能看成是谁？
Who else would I be?
それに、お前らも
威廉：而且，你们也……
And you guys too.
おい、なんすか？
格里克：喂，干嘛？
Hey, what's up?
無事で……あや、でもどうして？
威廉：平安无事……哎呀，但是为什么？
Safe... wait, but why?
何よ
珂朵莉：干嘛啦。
What is it?
あや、そうか。楽屋落ち連打で
威廉：哎呀，是吗。如果是连续爆内幕梗
Ah, I see. If it's an extra episode
本編の余韻を全力でぶち壊す番外編なら
威廉：全力破坏正篇余韵的番外篇的话，
destroying the main story's lingering mood with meta jokes,
そういうこともあるのか
威廉：这种事也是有可能的啊。
then I guess this is possible.
ていうかリーリァの奴、そこまで考えて
威廉：话说莉莉娅那家伙，该不会是考虑到这一步
Lillia didn't plan this farce just for this,
この茶番仕組んだんじゃねぇだろうな
威廉：才策划了这出闹剧吧。
did she?
ちょっと、もしもーし？
珂朵莉：喂，喂——？
Hello? Hellooo?
人の顔見たまま考え込まないで
珂朵莉：别盯着别人的脸沉思啊。
Don't get lost in thought while looking at my face.
ああ、えっとだな……うん
威廉：啊，那个……嗯。
Ah, um... yeah.
なに？
珂朵莉：什么？
What?
なんていうか……
威廉：怎么说呢……
How should I put it...
ただいま
威廉：我回来了。
I'm home.
え？
珂朵莉：欸？
Eh?
うん
珂朵莉：嗯。
Yeah.
おかえりなさい
珂朵莉：欢迎回来。
Welcome home.